De Hirsh Margules
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
De Hirsh Margules papers
1888-2001, bulk 1923-1965
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Margules, De Hirsh
5.6 linear feet
The papers of painter De Hirsh Margules measure 5.6 linear feet and date from 1888-2001, with the bulk dating from 1923-1965. The papers contain biographical material, and business and personal correspondence, including letters from Alfred Stiegliz, John Marin, Henry Miller, Max Schnitzler, Charles J. Connick, Louis M. Eilshemius, Alex King, and Myron Lechay. Also found are writings, printed material, scrapbooks, photographs, works of art and audio recordings documenting Margules' personal life and professional career.
Provenance
The papers were donated to the Archives in 2005 by Elita Agee.
Restrictions on Access
The De Hirsh Margules papers are open for research. Use requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
De Hirsh Margules (1899-1965) was a painter in New York, NY. Margules was born in Jasse, Romania and arrived in New York City at only ten months of age. His parents were in the Yiddish Theater; his father, Edouard was a playwright/director, and his mother, Rosa, was an actress. Margules received much of his art education outside of the conventional art institutional framework. Early on, he studied with Edwin Randby in Pennsylvania from 1917-1918, but it was really his neighbor, the painter Benno Greenstein, who encouraged Margules to pursue a career in the arts. From 1919-1921 he studied period architecture, design and decoration at the New York Evening School of Art and Design.
By 1922, Margules began working nights as a police reporter for the City News Association of New York, a job he would hold until 1942. However, he continued to study and paint during the day, this time working with Myron Lechay.
In 1927 Margules took a leave of absence from the City News Association to travel to Paris. He studied at the Musée du Louvre, and painted landscapes in Montmartre, Paris; Fontenay-près-Vézelay, Burgundy; and Tunis, Africa. In 1929 Margules returned to New York and met artist/dealer Alfred Stieglitz, who quickly became his most trusted friend and advisor. It was through Stieglitz that Margules was introduced to John Marin, Georgia O'Keeffe, Paul Rosenfeld, Stuart Davis and Jan Matulka. While Margules would benefit from his relations with all of these artists, it was John Marin who would become his most important mentor. He felt that Marin was the only one who could help him with the formal problems he was having with painting.
Margules lived most of his life in Greenwich Village and was a well-known member of the colorful and vivacious arts community. He was commonly recognized by his affable demeanor, but mostly it was his attire, particularly the dark blue beret that he was rarely seen without. To his friends he was known simply as "the Baron."
De Hirsh Margules has been called an abstract realist. He used saturated colors and bold textures in the construction of his abstract landscapes, but more specifically it was his interest in the concept of "time painting" or "time perspective" that propelled his work. It was through the physical rendering and representation of his subject matter that he explored the psychological concepts of time. From 1936-1937 Margules established "Another Place," an exhibition space set up in his New York City apartment at 43 West 8th Street. Over a two year period there were fourteen solo-exhibitions by Margules and other artists.
He taught painting in 1951 at Ball State College in Muncie, Indiana, and at the New York Equity Workshop in 1952. In 1951 Elaine de Kooning wrote a piece about his working methods in the December edition of Art News.
De Hirsh Margules died from a heart attack in 1965. He was 65 years old.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of painter De Hirsh Margules measure 5.6 linear feet and date from 1888-2001, with the bulk dating from 1923-1965. The papers contain biographical material, and business and personal correspondence, including letters from Alfred Stiegliz, John Marin, Henry Miller, Max Schnitzler, Charles J. Connick, Louis M. Eilshemius, Alex King, and Myron Lechay. Also found are writings, printed material, scrapbooks, photographs, works of art and audio recordings documenting Margules' personal life and professional career.
Biographical material consists of Margules' curriculum vitae, address books, war ration books, press credentials, passports, naturalization documents, membership and social security cards, and memorial material on De Hirsh and Blanche Margules.
Correspondence of De Hirsh Margules covers both personal and business matters. Family correspondents include his wife Blanche London, her parents, De Hirsh's mother Rosa and his sister Sam. There is correspondence with Jean and Harrison Horblit, friends and business associates of the Margules, as well as correspondence with his girlfriend, Marieli Kailin Mandel. Other correspondents include Alfred Stieglitz, John Marin, Henry Miller, Max Schnitzler, Charles J. Connick, Louis M. Eilshemius, Alex King, Myron Lechay, and two letters from New York Governor Herbert H. Lehman. There are single letters from Sasha Kolin; New York City Mayor John V. Lindsay; Lawrence F. O'Brien, special assistant to President John F. Kennedy; Buckminster Fuller. This last letter was not addressed exclusively to Margules. Other personal correspondence includes letters, postcards and greeting cards from family members and friends. Other business correspondents include galleries and museums such as Babcock Galleries, Museum of Modern Art, Whitney Museum of American Art, Niveau Gallery, Museum of Fine Arts Boston, Brooklyn Museum, Buffalo Fine Arts Academy, Ferargil Gallery, Feigl Gallery, Guggenheim Museum, Worcester Art Museum and Walker Art Center.
Writings consist mostly of poems by De Hirsh Margules, sometimes appearing in multiple draft forms, as well as a longer work titled "Mulberry Bend." Also included within the series are notebooks filled with poems and works of prose, the latter expounding upon his theories and ideas. Writings by other authors range from poetry to works of prose, criticism and biography, including A. Lincoln Gillespie, Jr., Kenneth Lawrence Beaudoin, David Weber, Aaron Frankel, James Grady, Dick Higgins, and Esther Gilman, among others. There are three illustrated writings by Alfred Jensen. Audio recordings contain a sound tape reel of De Hirsh Margules reciting his poems Rainbow and Mulberry Bend.
Printed material includes newspaper and magazine clippings, press releases, exhibition announcements, catalogues and books. Scrapbooks include printed material, newspaper and magazine clippings, and exhibition announcements on the career of De Hirsh Margules. Also included are two scrapbooks by Blanche London Margules, representing newspaper clippings of her writing, among others.
Works of Art include an oil painting on wood and sketchbooks by Margules. Also included are six collages in a series by Kenneth Lawrence Beaudoin titled "Eye Poems"; and text-based drawings/writings by A. Lincoln Gillespie, Jr.
Photographs, transparencies and slides include works of art by De Hirsh and Blanche London Margules. Also included are personal photographs of the Margules', their friends, family and students, and two folders of photographs of Marieli Kailin Mandel.
Arrangement
The De Hirsh Margules papers are organized into 8 series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1888-1978, undated (Box 1, 6; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1923-2000, undated (Box 1-3; 2.8 linear feet)
Series 3: Writings, 1936-1965, undated (Box 4; 1.0 linear feet)
Series 4: Printed Material, 1933-2001, undated (Box 5; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 5: Scrapbooks, 1922-1957, undated (Box 5, 7; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 6: Photographs, 1926-1992, undated (Box 5, 7; 0.8 linear feet)
Series 7: Works of Art, 1948, undated (Box 6, 7; 0.4 linear feet)
Series 8: Audio Recordings, undated (Box 6; 1 folder)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects-Topical:
Poets--New York (State)--New York; Painters--New York (State)--New York
Types of Materials:
Sketchbooks; Photographs; Works of Art; Poems; Oil paintings; Collages; Sound recordings; Scrapbooks; Writings; Notebooks
Names:
Miller, Henry, 1891-; Schnitzler, Max, 1903-; Stieglitz, Alfred, 1864-1946; Eilshemius, Louis M. (Louis Michel), 1864-1941; Mandel, Marieli Kailin; Marin, John, 1870-1953; Connick, Charles J., 1875-1945; King, Alex; Kolin, Sacha, 1911-1981; Fuller, R. Buckminster (Richard Buckminster), 1895-; Lechay, Myron, 1898-1972; Lindsay, John V.; Gillespie, Al Lincoln, Jr.; Gilman, Esther; Grady, James; Higgins, Dick, 1938-; Beaudoin, Kenneth Lawrence, 1913-; Weber, David A.; Jensen, Alfred, 1903-1981; Horblit, Harrison D.; Horblit, Jean; Lehman, Herbert H. (Herbert Henry), 1878-1963; Margules, Blanche London; O'Brien, Lawrence F.; Frankel, Aaron; Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.); Whitney Museum of American Art; Babcock Galleries; Niveau Gallery (New York, N.Y.); Buffalo Fine Arts Academy; Worcester Art Museum; Walker Art Center; Museum of Fine Arts, Boston; Brooklyn Museum; Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum; Ferargil Galleries; Feigl Gallery
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Material1888-1978, undated, Series 1:; (Box 1, 7; 0.2 linear feet)
  Biographical material consists of Margules' curriculum vitae, address books, war ration books, press credentials, passports, naturalization documents, membership and social security cards, and memorial material on De Hirsh and Blanche Margules.
  - Curriculum Vitae,undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Memorial Events, De Hirsh Margules,1965 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Memorial Events, Blanche London Margules,1948 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Address Books,undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Membership and Social Security Cards, 1926-1978, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Press Credentials, 1933-1942, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - War Ration Books, 1942-1947 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Registration Certificate for Selective Service, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Passports, 1926, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Naturalization, 1899, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Gerrit Vander Veenpenning Award, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - General Documents,1888 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Religious Document,1928 (Oversized material housed in Box 7) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Diaries and Autograph Book by Marieli Kailin Mandel,1936, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Oversized Religious Document,1928, (Oversized material from Box 1, Folder 13) (Box 7)
- Correspondence,1923-2000, undated, Series 2:; (Box 1-3; 2.8 linear feet)
  Included within this series is the personal and business correspondence of De Hirsh Margules. Correspondence with the family includes his wife Blanche London, her parents, De Hirsh's mother Rosa and his sister Sam. There is correspondence with Jean and Harrison Horblit, friends and business associates of the Margules, as well as correspondence with his girlfriend, Marieli Kailin Mandel. Other correspondents include Alfred Stieglitz, John Marin, Henry Miller, Max Schnitzler, Charles J. Connick, Louis M. Eilshemius, Alex King, Myron Lechay, and two letters from New York Governor Herbert H. Lehman. There are single letters from Sasha Kolin; New York City Mayor John V. Lindsay; Lawrence F. O'Brien, special assistant to President John F. Kennedy; Buckminster Fuller; and Armin D. Lehmann, a member of Hitler Youth and courier in the Führerbunker at the end of Adolf Hitler's rein. This last letter was not addressed exclusively to Margules. Other personal correspondence includes letters, postcards and greeting cards from family members and friends. Other business correspondents include galleries and museums such as Babcock Galleries, the Museum of Modern Art, the Whitney Museum of American Art, Niveau Gallery, Museum of Fine Arts Boston, Brooklyn Museum, Buffalo Fine Arts Academy, Ferargil Gallery, Feigl Gallery, Guggenheim Museum, Worcester Art Museum and Walker Art Center.
  The letters are arranged alphabetically by either institution or surname, while the material within each folder is arranged chronologically.
  - Estate Correspondence,1923-1968, 1994-2000, undated, (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 15-18)
  - De Hirsh Margules Housing,1939-1963 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Blanche Margules,1933-1935, 1945-1947, undated, (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 20-23)
  - Rosa Margules,1957-1962 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Sam Margules,1939, 1954-1962 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Family,1934-1937, 1948-1962 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Babcock Galleries,1953, 1993-1998, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Jean and Harrison Horblit,1964-1970, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Marieli Kailin Mandel,1945-1951, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 29-31)
  - Marieli Kailin Mandel,1951-1953, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - Marieli Kailin Mandel,1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Marieli Kailin Mandel,1959-1961, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
  - Marieli Kailin Mandel, American Citizenship Attempts,1942-1948, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - John Marin,1935-1936, 1953-1956, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Henry Miller,1935, 1940-1941, 1954, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - The Museum of Modern Art,1936-1949, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Niveau Gallery,undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Charles Norman,1964 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Dorothy Norman,1940-1949, 1961-1964, 1993-1994, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Parker Pen Company,1959-1961 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Mark Rosenthal,1989, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Sascha,1940 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Max Schnitzler,1942-1943, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Alfred Stieglitz,1933-1938, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence,1934-1936, 1952-1965, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Miscellaneous Addresses,undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence A,1936-1964, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence B,1934-1965, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 22-23)
  - Correspondence C,1934-1964, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 24-25)
  - Correspondence D,1940-1948, 1953-1964, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence E,1935-1946, 1953-1962 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence F, 1936-1964, 1973, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence G,1928-1965, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence H,1935-1965, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence I-J,1953-1965 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence K,1936-1964, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence L,1927-1965, undated, (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 4-6)
  - Correspondence M, 1936-1960, 1964, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 7-8)
  - Correspondence N,1939, 1953-1961 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence O,1947, 1964, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence P,1935-1965, undated, (4 folders) (Box 3, Folder 11-14)
  - Correspondence R,1935-1964, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence S,1936-1965, 1985, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 16-17)
  - Correspondence T,1935-1965, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence U,1949, 1963-1964, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence V,1936-1955, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence W-Z,1936-1964, 1989-1994, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 21-22)
  - Correspondence, Unidentified,1939-1954, undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Writings,1936-1965, undated, Series 3:; (Box 4; 1.0 linear feet)
  Writings consist mostly of poems by De Hirsh Margules, sometimes appearing in multiple draft forms, as well as a longer work titled "Mulberry Bend." Also included within the series are notebooks filled with poems and works of prose, the latter expounding upon his theories and ideas. Writings by other authors range from poetry to works of prose, criticism and biography, including A. Lincoln Gillespie, Jr., Kenneth Lawrence Beaudoin, David Weber, Aaron Frankel, James Grady, Dick Higgins, Esther Gilman, among others. There are three illustrated writings by Alfred Jensen.
  Audio recordings (series 8) contain a reel-to-reel tape of De Hirsh Margules reciting his poems Rainbow and Mulberry Bend.
  - Writings by De Hirsh Margules,1963, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Writings by De Hirsh Margules, St. Michael, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Writings by Others,1936-1965, undated, (3 folders) (Box 4, Folder 3-5)
  - Writings by Alfred Jensen,undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Poems by De Hirsh Margules (Box 4)
    - Mulberry Bend Draft (Part 1),1955, undated, (3 folders) (Box 4, Folder 7-9)
    - Mulberry Bend Draft (Part 2),undated, (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 10-11)
    - Miscellaneous,1936-1964, (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 12-13)
    - Miscellaneous,undated (3 folders) (Box 4, Folder 14-16)
  - Notebooks,1959, undated, (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 17-18)
  - Notes,1961, undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Travel Diary, Blanche London,1925 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Printed Material,1933-2001, undated, Series 4:; (Box 5; 0.2 linear feet)
  Printed material includes newspaper and magazine clippings, press releases, exhibition announcements, catalogues and books. Several of the books are inscribed by the authors including, Joseph Stella, Joseph King, Michael Fraenkel, Abraham Walkowitz and Henrietta Weigel.
  - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings,circa 1933-2001 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Press Releases,1941-1946, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Solo Exhibition Announcements,1939-1961 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Group Exhibition Announcements,1943-1964, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Catalogs,1944-1964, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Catalogs, signed,1944-1964 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Books (Box 5)
    - The Brooklyn Bridge by Joseph Stella (inscribed),undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - The Count by Joseph King (inscribed),1935 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Death in a Room by Michael Fraenkel (inscribed),1936 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Four Stories by Joseph Kling (inscribed),1936 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Improvisations of New York by Abraham Walkowitz,1948 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Paper Dolls Out of Rain by Henrietta Weigel (inscribed),1954 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Scrapbooks,1922-1957, undated, Series 5:; (Box 5, 7; 0.2 linear feet)
  Scrapbooks include printed material, newspaper and magazine clippings, and exhibition announcements on the career of De Hirsh Margules. Also includes two scrapbooks compiled by Blanche Margules, consisting of newspaper clippings of her writing, and one scrapbook compiled by Harry Salpeter.
  - De Hirsh Margules,1941-1945 (1 volume) (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - De Hirsh Margules, loose pages,circa 1943-1948, (Oversized materials housed in Box 7) (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - De Hirsh Margules, loose pages, 1936-1947, undated, (Oversized material housed in Box 7) (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Harry Salpeter,1947-1957, undated, (1 volume) (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Blanche Margules, 1922-1929,undated, (2 volume) (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Oversized Scrapbook by De Hirsh Margules, loose pages,circa 1943-1948, (Oversized material from Box 5, folder 14) (Box 7)
  - Oversized Scrapbook by De Hirsh Margules, loose pages,1936-1947, undated, (Oversized material from Box 5, folder 15) (Box 7)
- Photographs,1926-1992, undated, Series 6:; (Box 5, 7; 0.8 linear feet)
  Included are photographs, transparencies and slides of works of art by De Hirsh and Blanche London Margules. Also included are personal photographs of the Margules, their friends, family and students. There are two folders of photographs of Marieli Kailin Mandel.
  - Works of Art by De Hirsh Margules,undated, (2 folders) (Box 5, Folder 18-19)
  - Works of Art by Blanche London Margules,undated (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Works of Art in the collection of Jean Horblit, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - De Hirsh Margules,1932-1957, undated, (2 folders) (Box 5, Folder 22-23)
  - Personal Life,undated, (2 folders) (Box 5, Folder 24-25)
  - Blanche London Margules,undated (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Robert Berdecio,1963 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Edmond Mc Kenna,undated (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Marieli Kailin Mandel,undated, (2 folders) (Box 5, Folder 29-30)
  - Photographs by Miscellaneous Artists,1926, (Oversized material housed in Box 7) (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Transparencies of Works of Art by De Hirsh Margules,undated, (2 folders) (Box 5, Folder 32-33)
  - Transparencies of De Hirsh Margules,undated (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Transparencies of Personal Life,undated (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Glass Lantern Slide of Work of Art by De Hirsh Margules,undated (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Slides of Works of Art in the Collection of Jean Horblit,1992 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Slides of De Hirsh Margules,undated (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Slides of Marieli Kailin Mandel,undated (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Negatives of Marieli Kailin Mandel,undated (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Oversized Photographs by Miscellaneous Artists,1926, undated, (Oversized material from Box 5, folder 31) (Box 7)
- Works of Art,1948, undated, Series 7:; (Box 6, 7; 0.4 linear feet)
  This series consists of an oil painting on wood and sketchbooks by De Hirsh Margules. Also included are six collages in a series by Kenneth Lawrence Beaudoin titled "Eye Poems," and text-based drawings, writings by A. Lincoln Gillespie, Jr.
  - De Hirsh Margules, painting on wood,undated, (Oversized material housed in Box 7) (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - De Hirsh Margules, sketchbooks,undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Kenneth Lawrence Beaudoin, "Eye Poems,"1948 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - A. Lincoln Gillespie Jr., drawing,1948 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Oversized Oil Painting by De Hirsh Margules (on wood),undated, (Oversized material from Box 6, folder 1) (Box 7)
- Audio Recordings,undated, Series 8:; (Box 6; 1 folder)
  One sound tape reel (7-inch) recording of De Hirsh Margules reciting the written works Rainbow and Mulberry Bend.
  - De Hirsh Margules recitation of Rainbow and Mulberry Bend,undated (1 sound tape reel) (Box 6, Folder 5)